Guide to the L. C. Angle, Jr. Collection 1860-2001
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
L. C. Angle, Jr. Collection c. 1860-2001
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms2001-043
.5 cu. ft.; 1 container
Collection consists largely of materials related to the history of the Civil War in Virginia, particularly - but not limited to - copies and transcripts of Civil War letters, personal papers, and manuscripts. The collection also contains Civil War and post Civil War-related printed materials and memorabilia. Includes "Reminiscence of the Years 1861-1865" by Frank S. Robertson, "Battle of Brandy Station or Fleetwood" author unknown, "Robert Edwin Miles of the 21st Virginia Cavalry" by Mr. L. C. Angle, Jr. in The Historical Society of Washington Co., VA Bulletin: 2002.
Donor
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
L. C. Angle, Jr. is an 1940 alumnus of Virginia Tech. He is a resident of Abingdon, VA and a Civil War history enthusiast. Angle is also an active member in the Southwest Virginia Alumni Chapter. Colonel Angle also donated the Thomas W. Colley Collection. The Colonel L. C. Angle, Jr. Collection is also available in Abingdon, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
The L. C. Angle, Jr. Papers extend from 1860-1990. The collections consists of materials related to the history of the Civil War including copies and transcripts of letters, personal papers and manuscripts.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by document type, then chronologically.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1860-1862, 1921, n.d.
  - Photocopies and transcripts of Civil War Period letters including A. Anderson and Samuel T. Davidson. Includes a transcript of an order from Major General Jackson. A photocopy of a directive from R. E. Lee to General Jackson. 1862 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - James H. Barrett, confederate letters to his mother and his wife, Becca (photocopied and typewritten.) Barrett writes about The Seven Days Battle near Richmond. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Civil War Period letters (copies and transciptions) of James Clark (63rd Virginia regiment) to his wife, Martha and his sister. The letters are from Camp Narrows, Camp Tallperson and Camp Charleston, VA, Camp Near Franklin Depot, Southampton County, VA, Dalton, GA, Marietta, GA. Clark writes of seeing soldiers being branded as punishment for deserting in order to visit their wives. He also witnessed soldiers from a N.C. regiment being shot as deserters. Clark mentions General Joseph E. Johnston. Letter to Mr. Gallahan discussing debts. 1860, 1862-65 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Photocopy of David Perkins letters, 8th Tennessee Infantry. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Letter to the War History Commission of Washington County, VA, discussing Washington County's participation in the Civil War. 1921 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Manuscripts 1863-1964, 1990, n.d.
  - Typed copy of a handwritten manuscript by John Harvey Allen aboard the C.S.A. S.S. Alabama(subsequently fired upon and sunk.) 1863-1864 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - The 12th Ohio Volunteer Cavalry and"Lish" by Malcolm D. Stroad. Unpublished manuscript. 1990 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - "Battle of Brandy Station or Fleetwood" (photocopy). (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Transcribed document on "An Event in the Life of a Confederate Soldier," Battle of Kelly's Ford. Original in Thomas W. Colley Collection. (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Transcribed letters and history of the Waggoner brothers, Civil War soldiers. (Box-folder 1-10)
- Historical Sketches and Recollections 1968, 1977, n.d.
  - Historical Sketches of SW Virginia. "John B. Floyd, From Southwest Virginia to the Buchanan Cabinet, 1847-1856 by Edward L. Henson, Jr. 1968 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Reminiscences of Frank Smith Robertson (J.E.B. Stuart's staff) photocopy. F.S. Robertson was the son of Wyndam Robertson, Governor of Virginia in 1846. Includes photocopy of letter from J.E.B. Stuart. (Box-folder 1-12)
  - "Sketch of Carpenter's Battery," by Charles McAllister. 1977 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - A tribute to Jacob Swartz, Company D 1st Virginia Cavalry, a confederate soldier hired as a substitute by Alexander Galihan (orginal document) n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)
- Printed Materials 1800s, 1862-1899, 1902-1907, 1913, 1926, 2002
  - Newspaper articles relating to the Civil War. The Sun, Baltimore newspaper article "Furled Battle Flags of Union and Confederate. late 1890s, 1907 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - "Bull Run" Song of the Fourth Brigade (Confederate) (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Bulletin of the Historical Society of Washington County - Includes story of L. C. Angle's great great-grandfather who was in the 21st Virginia Cavalry. 2002 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Charter, By-Laws - Rules of Order and List of Offices and Members of R. E. Lee Camp 1, Confederate Veterans. The Benevolent Assn. of the Louisiana Division of the Army of Northern Virginia. 1884 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - "The South's Battle Abbey." "Four Years Under Marse Robert." Sixteenth Annual Renion of Confederate War Veterans.nformation Circular. Saltville, VA brochure. "A Monument to the Splendor of Human Character" by Hollins N. Randolph. "The Story of Camp Chase" by W. H. Knauss. "The Confederate Museum in The Globe" informational brochure. Typewritten copy of the cast iron monument on wouthwest slope of Snodgrass Hill - Trigg's Brigade. "Superb was the Day" by Gustav S. Faider (n.d. and no source.) Photocopied order signed R. E. Lee, Headquarters, 13 December 1862. Blank document - Register of Births and Deaths. 1902, 1926 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - "Offical Report of the History Committee of the Grand Camp C.V., Department of Virginia, Dr. Hunter McGuire. Reprint - Account of the Reunion at Gettysburg, PA, 50th Anniversay. Sterling's Southern Fifth Reader - miscellaneous sections. 1899, 1913 (Box-folder 1-20)
- Photographs n.d.
  - Photographs [3] and photocopied photographs [3] of Confederate Civil War veterans. (Box-folder 1-21)